When it comes to the artistic challenge
of marrying a film's visual language,
>> we should move to a small town where the
rule of law still exists.
>> With its narrative central themes,
>> you will not survive here.
You're not a wolf
and this is the land of wolves. Now,
>> there aren't many better examples to
look at
than Denal Nerv's Sicario. [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> In case you're in need of a quick
refresher, Sakario is a cold, brutal,
and highly pessimistic meditation on the
unfair and immoral power dynamics of
institutional corruption that
fundamentally ask the question, is it
morally justifiable to go to extreme
lengths to stop monsters if it means
that we become monsters ourselves in the
process
and helmed by legendary cinematographer
Roger Deakons, the visuals of Sicario
tell a very interesting story. So, I
wanted to take a closer look at a couple
of key moments that really capture the
essence [music] of what this film is
about in some very sneaky but super
interesting technical ways.
If you've seen the film right now,
you're probably expecting me to talk
about this bit here.
>> And that's exactly what I'm going to do.
Because to be honest, if I were to pick
the one shot that most obviously
captures the central themes and
conflicts of Sakario, it would be this
one. The first thing that stands out is
the visual conflict created by the
colors. If we then combine this with the
steadily building score,
the fact that it is a lingering 41
second long panning wide shot, and its
overall placement in the narrative,
Vnurv creates a perfect calm before the
storm effect that ratchets up the
tension very, very effectively. The
thing I wanted to spend time
highlighting here though is what an
artistic example of blocking along all
axes. This is the X-axis, the Z axis,
and most notably in this example, the
Y-axis. Deacons takes care of the Z axis
blocking quite smoothly by having the
second group of soldiers entering at a
very shallow depth in the frame. To be
honest, I don't think this does much
other than create a more interesting
three-dimensional shot, but when you're
dealing with silhouettes, that [snorts]
takes some skill. Then there's the
movement on the X-axis which has a
direction of right to left. Now left to
right is typically the most visually
acceptable X-axis motion for us humans.
It's how we read. [music]
It's how we represent time.
>> It's the direction we associate [music]
with progress, whether that's in film or
video games.
So, flipping this visual convention on
its head and having the direction in
which both the camera pans and the
soldiers move being right to left is
likely a deliberately unsettling example
of blocking and camera movement by
Deacons and Vnv. And tonally, it's
perfectly suited for this moment in
Sicario's narrative, especially when we
combine it with the blocking in the
Y-axis because crucially, the soldiers
are moving downwards through the frame
here. That's probably the thing I like
most about this shot because it just
nails the essence of the film so
succinctly. This is a film about
seemingly moral figures controversially
descending into the dark underworld of
illegality and doing some pretty corrupt
things.
>> You're afraid of the dark.
>> How do you show that to an audience like
this?
Shot compositions don't get much better.
And this brings me to the main thing I
want you to take away from this video.
The three-dimensionality of Sakario's
visual language, which is both
fascinating and thematic. Deacons and
VNV make use of the three dimensions of
their frames, the X-axis, the Z axis,
and most importantly, the Y-axis to
emphasize power dynamics, foreshadow
certain aspects of the story and its
characters, and bring a far greater
sense of verticality to the viewing
experience.
And so let's rewind a bit and pick up
here at arguably the most important
scene in the film. The moment that Emily
Blunt's character Kate Mesa decides to
begin her descent into darkness. Now,
there are so many interesting technical
decisions hidden in these frames. But I
wanted to start with this shot here. The
decision to introduce Josh Brolan's Matt
Graver in a group shot with the back of
his head to us. four fairly senior
looking characters positioned around him
and him not only being center of the
frame but the largest presence in the
frame. All of these decisions
strategically convey both his level of
seniority and mysteriousness. It's a
quick but slick introduction to his very
enigmatic elusive character. The most
interesting shot for me, however, is
here. There's so much to this
composition worth talking about.
Firstly, there's how the characters are
lit. All four men bathed in light with
Kate becoming some sort of silhouette as
she is framed in front of them,
intentionally and metaphorically putting
her in the dark as to what's actually
going on in this room.
More importantly, though, is what we can
discern from the blocking of this scene.
Kate's positioning on both the X and Zed
axes is pretty significant here. Yes, it
adds some nice depth to the frame having
Kate where she is, but the more
significant move is going from the
balanced composition of Graver's
introduction to a now unbalanced
composition.
It's subtle, but it's a nice way of
foreshadowing how by stepping into this
room, Kate's world and understanding of
the legal system is about to become more
and more crooked.
>> What the [__] are we doing? The other
and perhaps most important thing to note
is how Kate's silhouetted figure
vertically cuts the frame and separates
Graver from the rest of the men,
creatively conveying how he operates in
a very different world with a very
different sense of legality to these
men. We can tell how important it was to
communicate this dichotomy from this
very slight camera adjustment that
happens right here when this guy takes
his seat. And as Kate's boss says this,
>> "This is Matt Graver. He'll be leading
the team."
>> Not only does this very intentional
camera movement help to create the
visual disconnect between Graver and
these men that Vilner have clearly
wanted, it also helps to visually
reinforce the implicit sense of
superiority from Graver's mysterious
introduction shot. This subtle reframing
gives Graver just that little bit more
space in the frame than the other men
and ensures our gaze shifts over to him
along with Kate's with the net effect
being that we the audience feel his
presence in the room that much more.
It's the type of subtle storydriven
camera movement that Deacons often uses
in his compositions to bring another
level of dynamism to scenes like this
that would otherwise be quite flat,
elevating the storytelling of these
moments beyond their dialogue. And now
I'm going to scrape the barrel a bit and
consider things on the Y-axis where
Graver is placed ever so slightly lower
down in the frame. Maybe this is a sly
way of conveying how much more closely
he operates to the underworld of
illegality. Or maybe it was just an
unintentional byproduct of the way the
characters have been arranged in the
frame. As a firm proponent of Roger
Deacon's genius,
>> I'm pretty good cook actually. But um
>> and how often we see a sense of
verticality in this film cinematography.
I'm going with my initial
interpretation. I'll let you pick your
own lane. One last thing I enjoy about
this sequence is the camera work
employed throughout the conversation.
Firstly, when we look Kate in the eye,
she's either framed with a lot of
negative space around her, visibly
detached from her partner from a
distance dwarfed by the presence of the
men in front of her, or in closeup,
invading her personal space as she is so
impersonly picked apart by Graver.
>> Do you have a husband?
>> Divorced. Taken together, these
compositions all work very well to
visually communicate how isolated and
powerless Kate is throughout this entire
exchange and the male-dominated nature
of her world, which was a key aspect of
this story Vilner Nurv wanted to
emphasize. Overall, the interplay
between Kate and Graver is handled so
nicely by Deakons throughout the
sequence with Graver's deflective,
sarcastic nature captured in the way the
camera is never at eye level with him
until this final close-up shot here.
>> Do we get an opportunity at the men
responsible for today?
>> The only moment in which he tells the
truth.
>> The men who are really responsible for
today. Yeah. Now, that's how you use the
camera to tell a story. To me, these are
the types of scenes that separate the
best cinematographers from [music] the
rest of the pack. The cinematographers
who can take what in many ways could be
an extremely bland by the numbers
dialogue exchange and layer it with
these types of subtleties and
interesting visual storytelling
techniques that support the story's
thematic subtext so soundly. It's one of
the many things that Roger Deakons
nailed throughout his exceptional
career. and one of the things that I
think makes Sakario stand out as such a
fine example [music] of his
cinematography.
Thank you very much for watching.